Welcome to Lamrim.
And I thought I would review
what where we are. And first of all, I
want to thank everyone coming to Diamond
Mountain. It's good to see you. I see
from many countries and different a lot
of old friends. It's good to see you.
And
it's a guitar player here.
Aya.
All right. Okay.
And uh
I was going to review where we are.
Uh
we started as far as I can tell, I think
Angeli should know.
Uh
I have a record that we were doing
homeworks together in
So, I think we started in December of
2010.
Uh
we started this Lamrim and we knew it
would take about 10 years.
And it's going a little slower than we
predicted.
Uh but we're doing good.
Uh we have finished uh
Let's see.
It's 378
folios, which is 750
pages.
And we finished 90%. Okay.
Uh when we started
Am I pausing for translation, Timothy?
Okay.
When we started,
uh
we went straight to the part on
Shamatha and Vipassana. So, we went the
we started with the section on
meditation
and how to see emptiness.
And I did that because
the structure of Lamrim is
uh
rimbas.
And rimba means
uh meditations
that you do in a certain step-by-step.
So, Rimba means that.
So,
you know, since we're supposed to be
doing meditation step-by-step through
the 10 years,
I thought first we should
learn how to meditate.
Uh so, the first uh
courses that we did, we covered the
section on uh
shamatha, which is
how to prepare
your meditation for seeing emptiness,
and then vipashyana, which is how to see
the emptiness.
And we did those two sections, which are
basically
the last two of the six perfections. So,
we
we did that first.
And then we started back at the
beginning of the Lamrim uh with subjects
like how to find a teacher, for example.
And we've been working through that way.
So, pretty soon
uh we're going to hit shamatha again.
Uh
you know, after 10 years or 12 years,
and uh
then my plan is to jump to Lamrim
Chemal, which is Tsongkhapa's
uh Lamrim. And
his is a thousand pages long.
It's a little bit It's about a quarter
longer than this one.
And um
half of his presentation is about
meditation and emptiness. So, we'll come
back to meditation and emptiness.
And that's one of the greatest
presentations in history.
So, uh that'll take us another 3 years
or so.
Uh sorry.
6 years.
So, uh we'll finish around 2000
30, hopefully.
All right.
And uh my teacher
taught this Lamrim
uh
for, I don't know,
25 years. He took I heard it three times
from him.
Uh I think it's
probably the greatest book ever I've
ever read.
And uh
And so it's a it's a pleasure to go
through it. And and I think uh
it's not like you finish it and you and
then you
you just finish it and and then you're
done. It's not like that. Every time he
finished it, he started it over again.
Uh
and uh I think it's uh
it's not like reading a book. It's more
like an experience.
I think the javelina are here.
Uh
good to see you guys.
Right? Oh, no, it's a coyote.
Uh right out this window.
Uh
Can you see him?
Behind me. He's hiding.
Behind that white rock.
It's pretty. It's very pretty.
Yes.
Uh yeah. So
So I mean a book like this is more of an
experience. Uh and you you don't really
finish. You just start over again.
And to me
for the you know uh
my teachers uh
the last 25 years that he taught it was
very comforting to always have Lamrim
going on. So he taught many many
uh
deep subjects, but he would always come
back to the Lamrim a couple times a
week. And
I think it's a very
comforting thing to to be going through
Lamrim for your whole life. I don't
think you ever graduate. I I it's
it's nice to have someone who can
keep giving you
you can see him now look quick.
Still? Oh, it's a fox it's a fox
actually.
Yeah.
He's showing his butt to
and he's eating soap or something.
Diamond Mountain fox.
It's not a cat.
It's a fox I think.
It's a fox.
I think.
Foxy maybe. All right.
By the way, they're very shy. It's very
rare to see one like that.
Must be a good sign.
Uh
so where we are in the we're at the
point um and I I this is maybe the most
important
part of the class
where he announces where we are.
And he says uh
and
and by the way, I always in long rim I
like to explain the text literally and I
will read it in Tibetan and I will
explain it and uh
I was talking to my wife. We drove over
from San Diego
yesterday the day before.
And
and
she was asking me about Tibetan like
what
what language family is Tibetan and it
just dropped out of the sky. There's no
relation to any language.
Uh it really does seem to be a divine
language and then of course Sanskrit so
uh we'll be studying both, okay? But, um
I like to read the
Tibetan. This book is the best
Tibetan ever written
uh in history.
And it was the end of the Tibetan
language as we know it. Uh
Tibet was lost uh
short shortly after this was written.
Tibet was lost, and the language has
been uh
corrupted.
I I met a person recently. I met two
people who speak,
you know, real Tibetan,
older Tibetans, uh
and it was incredible. As we have
I was with Sugden,
and uh it was so sweet to hear uh
those are the last people who can speak
it properly.
And this book is the last and greatest
book ever written in Tibetan. And uh
so that's a that era has passed.
Uh
so he says here
uh
Kunzang Chanchub Gyaltsen, we're going
to study
bodhicitta,
Chanchub Gyaltsen, but then he says
Kunzang,
which means for $100.
False.
What did you say, Rob?
Yeah, 50 bucks 50 bucks each, okay? Cat
and Rob, 50 bucks each. Now, the rules
of this money giving
All right, guys. Uh
you have to collect it.
I I was teaching in Japan last week,
and uh
some older gentleman came up after the
talk, and he said, "You owe me $100."
And I said, "No, I don't." And he said,
"Yeah,
you came to Japan 5 years ago, and you
never paid me."
And I'm like,
"The new rule is you have to collect,
okay? It's not my fault if you don't
collect, okay? Who do you collect from?
Uh Alice right here, Jigme.
And you can collect from her. Please
collect it in a reasonable time.
Okay? I can't guarantee I'll have any
money in 5 years. So
So she's there, just ask her, she'll pay
you, okay? 50 bucks a day.
Yeah, whatever.
Then we have to
We have to find something to put in the
bank. Yeah, okay.
Uh so why would he say we're going to
study fake bodhicitta?
Yeah, good. It's the perception of
emptiness. Yeah, good. So too bad I
didn't offer any money for that,
Rebecca.
Yeah, it's kind of weird that to for an
author to say, "Let's study fake
bodhicitta," you know?
And then uh this whole section
is fake bodhicitta. Fake bodhicitta
means
uh it's a ultimate love
for all beings.
Uh but not necessarily understanding
emptiness, okay?
And uh what we call real bodhicitta or
ultimate bodhicitta
would be the direct perception of
emptiness, okay?
And there's a debate whether that would
involve
uh
loving all beings, for example. And
Sakya's position is that you can see
emptiness directly without a love for
all beings, okay?
Uh all right.
Uh
so it says here
Lojong Wola, so
$50 for Lojong Wola.
Training the heart.
Yeah,
uh
a good heart. Yeah, okay, good. $50.
That you collect from the bus. Yeah, lo
jong wang la
is the root of the word for
lo jong.
I just say it with a different accent,
right? Lo jong wang la means if you want
to train your mind
this is what lo jong means. Lo jong la
means chang chuk yi sem lo jong la.
Means training your mind in this
ultimate love, okay? Training your mind
in ultimate love. So, when you see a ACI
course called
lo jong, it means chang chuk yi sem la
lo jong la. Studying
training your mind in bodhicitta. So, to
call it uh mental training or something
like that is uh
I think it's misleading.
Uh it's it's training your mind in love
or compassion, okay?
Uh lo jong la. So, here he uses it.
And then he's going to Tim
Uh
look for
start gift 43.
Look for gift 43.
This is the 43rd retreat.
And you can look for the
Well, I might have changed it since I
sent it to you last night.
Uh
we're not there yet. Well, I think so.
No, we're not You don't have it. I'm
sorry.
I uh
I I added it this morning.
Uh
so, I can I will but I will Yeah, will
catch up to you.
And that'll be uh Pel key day.
P D P A L T Y I
S D E
Pel key day Shri Sena
Okay.
So, the outline here and
the flow of what we're doing, you should
know it and you should be meditating on
it this week. Okay? So, you should
Here's
Here's where we introduce what you're
going to be meditating on.
And I'll go through meditations with you
briefly.
Uh
and then we will
we'll have longer sessions
uh with Tim and his stuff about how to
do the meditations. So, I'll I'll give
you a
I'll give you the bare bones.
And there's basically five different
topics we're going to be meditating on.
And that's what Lamrim means, like the
topics of the path. Okay? So, we'll this
week uh especially at Diamond Mountain
on the By the way, the stupa looks
great. I just noticed it.
Fox in the stupa. Uh
There'll be five basic topics. And And
it's a beautiful flow. Okay? It's a
really interesting flow. So,
first he says, "So, you should
write this down or try to remember these
five. Okay? Five topics that we're going
to meditate on.
Okay? Dam ba duction nyam ba gom ni.
And that That's called a meditation
where I
and the other people around me
have an equal right
to get what they want. Me Me
and the people around me
have an absolutely equal right
to
to find happiness. Okay? Your right to
happiness and my right to happiness
is totally equal, okay? And that's
Dakshin
Nyamba. You've heard Dakshin Nyemjay.
Uh
Dak means me.
Shen means other people.
Then Nyemjay, you heard the word
Nyemjay, but it's actually two pieces,
okay? So, there's two practices. Nyamba
means
recognize that we all have an equal
right to happiness. That's called
Dakshin
Nyam.
And then Jay means uh
where you exchange yourself with others.
And it's not what it sounds like.
It's It's uh It's deeper than it sounds,
okay? It's not just
putting yourself in someone else's
place. I mean, that's also a good
practice,
and that's a good place to go to,
uh but it's it's a little more
sophisticated than that.
And And so, when you say
What do they call it?
Equalizer? I don't know. People have
strange translations.
Uh
but uh
it's not just exchanging self and
others. It's It's deeper than that. And
we'll get to it. We'll go through it,
okay?
Uh
Those of you who are going through DCI,
you've you've had it already. So,
uh Dakshin Nyamba Gomani.
And
uh
Yeah.
Uh
Then he says He says this. Um
Tomar ngakong shib dangnyem neyung kycha
baro ma tukyi pa na kong shib dangnyem
neyung kycha baro.
Uh
Dakshin Jewa de ngöndu.
Before you could ever get to
the second part, okay? Uh so, Dakshin
Nyamba means
to come to a deep meditative
understanding that the right of other
people's to happiness is is equal to
your own.
Uh
all the time, every day, in everything
you do.
And then dog chen zhe wa
uh to actually exchange yourself with
others.
Uh that needs some
preliminary work. So, there's
preliminary work. The first great topic
here
is to realize that the right
of others to happiness is equal to your
right, okay? Then the second great topic
is uh dog chen zing ki gyen god du men
ni sam pa, which means uh recognize
the great uh
problems that are created in your own
life
by
taking care of yourself first.
Okay? The the great
tragedies that result in your life
whenever you take care of yourself
first.
Or you prioritize yourself first. And
so, there's a whole section on
how that messes up your life. What a
problem that is. Every day, all day,
every time you try to take care of
yourself first.
Uh
it's a disaster. So, that's the second
You could say the second uh step here is
the disaster
of trying to take care of yourself
before other people.
Or prioritizing yourself.
And I think there's a place here where
you could say
uh
we're not trying to be a martyr.
Uh it's just a recognition that we all
have an equal right to happiness. So,
you don't have to say, "I'll take care
of you instead of me."
Uh
it's that let's take care of all of
ourselves together
as one being, okay? So, it's not like uh
it's not a Buddhist practice to uh
deny yourself happiness or I'll be
unhappy until you get to Nirvana and
then I'll come later.
That's just a koopa ootz ootz.
Dumb ass.
Uh
so,
it's not like that. We all supposed to
cross the finish line at the same time.
And that's nice.
Okay. So, so
the second great
meditation here
is that uh
trying to prioritize my happiness above
everybody else's happiness
is just to recognize that it hasn't
worked out in your life so far.
You know, I'm 70 years old. Like, maybe
it would be a nice
line to start thinking differently.
And I don't I don't know how old some
people here are. Kids, but
uh
but I mean, at some point in your life,
you have to draw a line
and say, "This doesn't work out." You
know, trying to take care of myself
first,
and ignoring other people's
pressing
uh needs, desperate needs.
It It just won't It will never work out.
It's It's uh faulty. It's
It's broken. It's a broken way of
thinking and it and it it will never
You devote yourself to your own
happiness, but you therefore fail
to reach your own happiness. It's a It's
a disaster. It's a built-in
disaster. It will never work.
Uh
It just can't work. So, so trying to
you know, saying, "I Look, yes, I can't
handle
taking care of everybody. You know, I
just got to take care of myself first.
Uh it doesn't work that way. I'm sorry.
You And you can take care of everyone.
Okay? Don't think you cannot. You can.
You have
that that's your blessed
capacity. That's your enlightened
capacity. Every person
who's listening to this
has the power
to take care of everybody else
and themselves at the same time.
And And it And And that's faulty
thinking.
Okay? Number three.
Shen chen zhen gi yan deng go du mi sang
ba.
The third of the five great meditation
topics that we will be covering.
Ding ding. Is
ye jin
Uh
is to is the opposite. Uh if you learn
to take care of others with the same
kind of
passion
that you take care of yourself
uh
how many beautiful things will happen.
That's the third part. That's the third
great
topic
in learning to develop
bodhicitta
fake bodhicitta. Nice. Okay. Fake
bodhicitta.
Why is it fake? What's real bodhicitta?
The direct perception
The direct perception of emptiness.
Okay.
Cuz you cannot take care of others
until you see emptiness directly. Okay?
You can't really.
All right? You can
practice and you can get used to the
idea, but you can't really do anything.
Okay? You can't really help them until
you see emptiness directly. You don't
have anything to offer.
Okay? You don't have anything much
different. You can feed people
then they'll get hungry again, you know,
you can
pull them out of a war zone and then
they'll be a war wherever they go,
and things like that, okay? So, until
you see
emptiness directly,
you don't really have anything to offer
other people equally. You see what I
mean? Okay? So, the third great topic
is thinking about examples
of people who have who truly taken care
of others, and that's where we are.
That's the section where we are.
And we had
uh Lamrim Steps of the Path teaching in
Kyoto.
Uh and we will continue uh to do a lot
of ACI programs at Diamond Mountain
and in Kyoto
uh because
it it it it helps people in Asia. There
are so many people in Asia
who who want to come to Lamrim.
It's difficult to travel to United
States. There's a lot of dumb
rules about
visas and stuff, and and Kyoto is
extremely
convenient for almost anybody. Uh can
travel there easily.
And so, we'll be doing
uh we'll kind of split the time
between Diamond Mountain. We'll be here
for the usual
two
retreats during the one-week spring
and during the one-week autumn.
Uh
and uh we hit it just right. By the way,
I schedule my whole year around these
two retreats cuz we have to come here
when the weather's really good.
So,
uh
so, we'll keep doing that here. We were
doing
uh retreats in Mexico
uh every summer because Guadalajara is
is I think the only major city in the
world
which has the same temperature
every month of the year.
Uh
it's pleasant every month of the year.
So, we will continue We're COVID's over.
And even if it's not over, we don't
care.
And uh
we're going to
resume in Guadalajara uh this summer.
Uh right, Tim, what month?
In July.
Which Which dates?
August.
5th to 11th.
6th to 11th.
5th or 6th to 11th, something like that.
So, we'll be going back to Guadalajara
which we used to do uh every summer and
we'll start again.
And then we'll be doing uh Asia
retreats
uh probably Kyoto
in December.
Yeah. So, we'll be doing Lamrim uh four
times a year. We'll go back to four
times a year.
Hopefully Geshe La won't get distracted.
Hopefully, we'll finish the Lamrim.
Hopefully, I won't find anything else to
teach
during those retreats. We'll still try
to cover Nagarjuna.
I still owe you half of the fifth on on
fifth
great teachers Medicine Buddha teaching.
We didn't finish that. So, um that's
probably in the fall, right?
Okay.
Uh
still to do, still ahead of us are steps
four and five, okay? Still ahead of us
are four and five, okay? What is four?
Uh Dagsang Gyalwa Sangpo, which means
the actual practice
of exchanging myself and others, okay?
Uh so, we'll get to that.
We're going to get to that in about 2
days or something like that. And we'll
actually learn how to uh exchange myself
and others. Again,
it's more complicated than it sounds
like. It's not just trying to imagine
how the other person feels. That's not
the whole thing, okay?
Uh
it's a
it's actually a very challenging
meditation. And and it's deeper than
that. Okay, number five,
uh
delak ten main tonglen gom su.
Uh
then you're ready to do tonglen. Then
you're ready to start tonglen, the
famous tonglen meditation, giving and
taking meditation. Uh giving happiness
to other people, taking away their
problems, okay? Taking away their
suffering. So, you need a lot of work
to get to the first meditation that they
teach
everybody in the monastery, okay? I
mean, kids
around age seven or eight, they start
with tonglen meditation.
And we're going to work for
12 years to get to it.
All right. We're just about to get to
it, all right? And and then So, I'm
going to repeat the five and uh
and that'll be the basis of our
meditations this week, okay? First one
was
uh equal rights, okay? You could just
say equal rights, okay? People have
equal right to happiness. You don't have
a right
to work for your happiness first. You
don't have that right, okay?
Number two,
uh
think about the problems
of trying to take care of yourself
first. It's a
it just doesn't work. And it never will.
So,
you know, give it up. Okay?
Give it up. And you can hang on to it
for another year or 10 years or
50 years and sooner or later you're
going to have to
face it.
That trying to take care of yourself,
prioritizing what you want
over what other people want is is doomed
to fail.
It will never work. Okay? And I don't
know how many years you have to live on
this planet before you get that.
The the whole purpose of Lam Rim
is for the older, wiser people
to tell their younger, foolish people
what to do.
And
and it's tradition
for about 50,000 years that the younger
people don't listen.
And I also didn't listen when I was
young.
But
you can try and try
take care of yourself first
and it's just hopeless. It does not
work. And and you just
you know,
you can wait 50 years and then figure it
out or you can listen to the
gray hairs or the no hairs.
Okay.
Uh
So, Dag Tenzin Kunga Drolchok number
two, it doesn't work
to try to take care of yourself first.
Okay? Number three, what?
Yeah, it's a lot cooler. It works a lot
better.
You have to kind of overcompensate
slightly
and and try to
take care of others cuz it has been zero
so far.
So, yeah. Try to enjoy
how much fun it is
to take care of other people and to
focus on what other people want.
And try to just try it out like a new
pair of jeans,
you know, and keep just see how fun it
is
and how satisfying it is to take care of
other people. Okay, number three.
Number four,
the actual
exchange of yourself and others, which
is not what it sounds like, okay? It's
deeper than that.
And then number five,
yeah, then you're qualified to do this
first meditation that all the
seven-year-olds learn,
uh
which is tonglen, okay? So, the
implication is
you need a lot of preliminary work
to do tonglen.
Tonglen is not easy.
Tonglen is a very advanced practice.
And you need a lot of
contemplations and meditations before
that, okay? And we'll do some.
Okay.
You want to Let's do one right now,
okay?
All right. So, get ready to meditate.
We'll Grandpa will lead you in a short
meditation.
Those Vietnamese people call me Ong Noi,
which means wise one, I think.
Or grandpa.
We'll do about 10 minutes.
When you meditate in a group,
you have a bigger obligation to
Turn off your cell
Be quiet.
Yeah, if your cell phone's not off, you
might want
Blow your nose now.
Okay, here we go.
This week I'm going to I want you to try
on
a new
a
way to start a meditation which is a
hundred breaths instead of ten.
And uh
I don't know if I'm getting more
distracted as I get older, but I
ten breaths doesn't work for me.
And doing ten breaths four four five
times doesn't work for me.
And
a hundred does work. That's about six
minutes or so. Okay?
So, we're going to do try to count a
hundred breaths.
You're allowed to continue if you go
out. Just try to remember where you
were.
Okay. So, here we go.
Hundred breaths.
Exhale's the first half, inhale's the
second half.
Mhm.
Now, I'd like you to think about
uh some interaction you had with someone
probably yesterday,
but somebody you spent maybe half an
hour with in the last few days.
And just try to choose one of those
interactions with another person, at
least half an hour that you spent
together.
And try to remember when it was that you
were hoping to get out of that
interaction. Like I I
spent uh the last 5 days with my wife.
We went to take care of my mom who had a
stroke.
And uh
I was spending a lot of time
uh with Veronica and
think I was
hoping to
I was hoping to work on Sue Gang's text.
Uh
so that was kind of in the back of my
mind.
What were you thinking about
when you were with this person?
What were you
What did you want to do during that
time?
And then what do you think the other
person wanted to do during that time?
What What
Based on what they spoke and based on
how they were acting,
uh
what did you what do you guess
they most wanted to do
while you were together? What was in
their mind?
And what would they enjoy? What would
they have enjoyed doing
during that time you were together?
I think my wife at that time she was
really focused on helping my mom.
And um
she has a list of other people that
she's helping and I think she would have
liked to
have
really focused our time on them.
And you could
sacrifice what you wanted to do.
And you could just do what the other
person wanted to do,
uh
and that probably won't
be sustainable. You probably cannot
uh
continue doing that. You also have
important things to do. You have
things that you would like to do.
And then they have things that they
would like to do.
So,
Phunsumba,
could there be a third
alternative? And Bodhisattvas
are constantly thinking
of Phunsumba. Phunsumba means is there a
third choice?
Uh
I know what my wife would like to do
today.
I know what I would like to do today.
And is there some kind of clever
uh
innovative, creative way
that we could both do what we want
uh
and be together,
and and still be interacting,
and still spend the day together. Is
there some way
that we could both do
deeply get into what we want
uh
individually
and
create some third possibility of
our relationship or our interaction
where somehow we do both
at the same time better
than if we were not together. Uh
Is Is there some way
that I could
work on Sukha Gakpo's translation, and
is there a way that we could be serving
my mom and
and my wife's other
clients
and
is there some way that we could
do both
at the same time. We have an equal right
to do what we would like to do.
And is there some really super creative
way
that we could help each other
do what each of us wants to do
and do it better
than if we tried to do what we want
alone
or at the expense of the other person.
And this is the Bodhisattva's
way of life. They are not
sacrificing what they would like to do.
They are not selfishly just doing what
they would like to do.
They are finding creative ways
that everyone can get what they want at
the same time.
So, think about that interaction and
think of try to think of a
third
choice between the two choices.
Something
some way that you could have
achieved
what both people wanted
uh during the same day.
So, what my wife and I did
we blocked out a time in the morning.
She enjoys walking and
we were in California. She enjoys
walking at the at the ocean.
So, she would go for a walk.
We just make a deal.
And
and she might be collecting her thoughts
for the day or she might be
preparing
her list of things to do today to help
other people.
And then during that time I I I will
work on Seung Sahn's great translation.
And
then we get together
at the end of the morning and
we combine our lists.
She has a list of
people she would like to
for us to help together and I have my
own list.
So, we spend a few minutes
combining our lists
and find working out a way that we can
do both during the day
together.
Try to think if there's some kind of way
you could have done that with this other
person
in your interaction this week. It's It's
called
Pung Sum Ba. It's called
creative
super creative
middle way
between doing what they want
only what they want and doing only what
you want. Is there some
super creative way to
do both?
And no person sacrifices. Each person's
goals for the day are equally important.
Okay, and then slowly open your eyes.
Come back.
Take a stretch.
Ah.
And then I think if you're like me,
uh
So, I I used to have I remember when I
came to Diamond Mountain first, I had uh
80 students in New York.
Uh
and we came here to
to learn Diamond Way together.
They did uh 7 years of preparation in
New York, and then we came here and we
did 7 years
uh of Diamond Way.
And then we all graduated.
Uh
a lot of people did 3-year retreat.
Now, it's 200,000 students
uh in the world. So, there are 200,000
students in the There's about 15
organizations now.
And there's about uh 200,000 students.
Uh
So, I have these demands on my time. It
went from 80 to 200,000.
Uh and I have
the demands on my my time are are you
know
about that much more.
You know,
uh
and I can't uh
I can't do what I do with my wife, you
know. I can't try to do what 200,000
people
would like
the way I used to do with 80 people, you
know. So, unfortunately, I have friends
many friends in this room from the 80
people days.
And they're like, "Could I just have an
hour of your time, guest number one?"
I'm like, "No, things have changed, you
know."
But uh
By the way, I will spend time and I do
spend time and I you know, always have
time somehow.
But uh
you can't
accommodate 200,000 people the way you
can 80 people. It's not possible.
And I'm not saying you should go crazy
and try to give an hour to 200,000
people. We calculated it the other day.
It would take 16 years or something.
Uh 16.6 years. Uh
so
it's not about that. It's not uh more
clever time management.
Uh
Time is also empty.
Uh time can also be bent and shortened
or lengthened. Einstein proved it with
Mercury
traveling around the Sun.
And uh the light that comes from Mercury
to the Earth
is bent by the gravity of the Sun.
So, it it can be proven
uh as Einstein predicted
that uh
the light Mercury seems to slow down as
it exits the arc of the Sun.
And uh
time slows down. Time is a circle.
Uh space is curved.
And uh it takes longer for light to get
to us if it has to pass by the Sun,
which means you are looking at the past.
You are traveling in the past. When you
look at Mercury in a telescope,
literally you are traveling in the past.
Uh
you time travel.
And the new web telescope is just even
more
It's even more the case. You can be in
the past. You can observe the past
directly
as it happens.
And so,
the Bodhicitta's method
to accommodate
all people equally
has to do with emptiness of time and
space, okay?
We find time. We create time.
And we And we mess with I almost said a
bad word. We mess with space.
And then we can serve
more people. So, the two kinds of
Bodhicitta
dovetail.
The two kinds of Bodhicitta help each
other.
It's It's impossible
for me in a normal time-space to do what
I used to do.
And it's impossible to accommodate
20 200,000 people the way I accommodate
my wife
this week.
Unless I can work with emptiness, okay?
So, you need that tool. If you want to,
in my opinion,
the reason he started the discussion
by saying the fake Bodhicitta
was he was implying you got to use the
ultimate Bodhicitta also, or you cannot
ever
serve
people equally, okay? You cannot
accommodate
countless beings'
wishes for equal time
unless you can mess with time.
Okay? And you'll get better at it, okay?
You'll get better at it. The first the
the desire has to be there
to help
hundreds of thousands of people. The
first the desire has to be there.
And then that drives you. What's it?
Necessity is the mother of invention,
you know. If you're hungry enough
to serve hundreds of thousands of
people,
uh you will find a way. Cuz the human
mind is
the capacity your capacity to serve
others is infinite. You literally have
an infinite capacity. You just have to
be pushed to it.
Okay?
Good?
All right.
We'll talk more about it. Uh we have a
We have about 10 minutes for questions.
And then Tim, I'll I'll
defer to you how you want to do it in
this room or you want to do it online or
uh I'll just do you choose questions and
Okay, we'll start in here
with the blue box and
or the gray box.
And any And by the way, they the
questions don't have to be relevant.
You can do any question you've been
saving up for a year or something. I
don't care.
Uh thank you.
You can ask them to ask questions in the
chat and we'll kind of
And if you have questions uh
to ask in the chat,
uh send them in.
And don't be shy and and if we'll try to
cover them in the next
session if we can. Okay, go ahead.
Thank you for the opportunity.
I have a question related to this
training and also to
level two advanced.
So, could you comment on the link
between
tonglen meditation
and what I consider the most important
idea in uh
level two advanced that I am the
opposite of everybody that I am not.
I
I I didn't catch the first thing between
coffee meditation, did you say?
Between uh tonglen meditation, so what
we are doing this week.
Okay. Okay.
And
Oh, yeah.
the main idea from Level 12 last
Yeah, okay. Good. Good.
Uh that's a deep question. So,
just as a background,
uh DCI, Diamond Cutter Institute,
which mainly uh
we have about 15 organizations. Um each
one has its own niche.
Each one is trying to serve people in a
different way.
We just opened a university, an MBA and
EMBA university, uh
because we didn't have a degree program
accredited. You couldn't get a degree
that anybody else would accept
uh in any of our 14 organizations. So,
we built a a university. We're building
a university in Sedona and Kyoto. And we
had our first classes
uh
2 weeks 2 weeks ago.
And it's going very well, and we are
going to get accredited and
it's an extraordinary
expenditures.
Uh
and and extraordinary donations. And so,
we we have literally uh millions of
dollars of support, and it's going very
well.
And uh we actually have
students. The first class is pretty big.
So, uh
each each different uh organization is
meant to
uh address a a different need of people.
And uh so, DCI,
the purpose is to address the needs of
normal people uh who are not necessarily
Buddhist.
Okay? And so, we tried to make DCI
secular. DCI doesn't teach
religion.
Uh
it teaches
how to be successful
at home, in your family, and how to be
successful in in a business.
And that's uh
last year 138,000 students uh took
courses. Some are repeats, some took two
courses, okay?
But 138,000 courses were were taken last
year.
Uh
we
uh made a goal
of having 12
courses. And we So, every year we set a
goal to create a new course.
And there's courses we just finished a
course in addiction, for example, how to
overcome addictions
uh
in Taiwan in June, right, Sigrid?
We'll be uh teaching level seven, which
is about how to see emptiness directly.
And by the way, if you miss that, you
are really stupid.
Uh you don't deserve to see emptiness
directly.
Uh
just kidding. No.
Now, there's a jackrabbit straight back
straight behind
with the long ears. Uh
Think
Unfortunately, desert animals tend to
move.
Uh
But they have these huge ears.
We call jackrabbit.
Special kind of rabbit.
Uh
Where was I? Yeah, so that that's DCI's
goal. We finished the 12 years
uh and then people said, "What are you
going to do?" And I said, "Well,
I I what I usually do which is 12
advanced levels."
So, we finished the second advanced
level uh last year, I think. Well, I
wrote it last year and we
we uh released it in December, I think.
And that level, the second advanced
level, was
really focusing on how your mind
creates objects.
And as Annelie mentioned, one of the
most important aspects
of how the mind creates objects
is that we
cancel everything an object is not. And
the classic example is being in the
train station, maybe I was with Walter
and dude, I don't remember, in Germany
and we were with Sylvia Engelhardt.
And we had like 5 minutes to catch a
train. I think it was Minken or
something.
And uh
And we got there with all these bags and
all these people and and I said, "Well,
let's get on the train." And she said,
"No,
we don't have any tickets."
And I'm like, "Who's got the tickets?"
And she said, "There's a lady meeting us
here."
And there's like 5,000 people there
milling around and I'm and the train is
getting ready to leave and I'm like,
"Wait to lady."
And she says,
uh
"And then it was a natural process of
elimination. She said, 'Well, first of
all, she's a lady. So, I just cancel all
the men in the train station. Like I
don't even look at them. I just see
2,500 ladies.'
And then I say, 'Well, is she tall or
short?' She's tall. 'Okay, cancel all
the short ladies. Now I'm down to 1,200
ladies, you know. And then I said, 'Does
she
Does she have a coat on?' Yes. 'Oh, 600
ladies.
Uh okay, then what color is the coat?
Red. Cancel all the yellow coats, the
blue coats, the green coats, you know,
and we're down to like 20 ladies, 20
tall ladies with red coats, you know.
And then I say, you know, what her hair
look like, you know. One day I was
looking for a lady uh
a lady at the What is it called? The
Lincoln Center.
And
the only clue I had to go on was she was
a modern dancer.
So, I was looking at people's calves.
And uh
I found her.
Uh
and uh
you know,
so that's a called a process of
elimination. You cancel
things until you arrive at the one
you're trying to reach. And your mind is
doing that
anytime you perceive anybody. So, my
mind is doing that
with my wife. I'm canceling
The only way I can see my wife
to discuss who gets to do what they want
uh
is to cancel everything that's not my
wife.
And that's just a fact of human
perception. You you see things
uh by canceling who's not the thing you
want to see.
It's the same as the lady in the train
station. So, the human mind
uh creates archetypes
by canceling everything that's not the
thing you're looking for. You never
actually meet someone
to discuss who's going to get to do what
they want. Uh
you you meet people
and you recognize those people by
canceling everyone who they are not.
Now, there's a huge philosophical
discussion.
Do you actually have to perceive
everything they are not to cancel it?
And the obvious answer is
you don't have time.
Okay? I don't have time to cancel every
single woman in San Diego to get to my
wife to decide who's going to do what
they want.
You know, you do it through
representative examples. So, I cancel
general other women in the in in my part
of San Diego, and I reach my wife, okay?
And that's that's a process
of of elimination.
Uh if you understand that,
uh you're close to emptiness. You're
much much closer to emptiness.
And then, if you work on that idea,
which is advanced level two in DCI, if
you work on that idea,
uh you can see the emptiness of your
wife,
and then you can
uh mess with
reality,
and you're more able to come up with
these
very
uh innovative solutions to pleasing
everybody,
which is once you agree that everyone
has an equal right to happiness.
You do have to please everybody.
Okay? And get used to it, okay? That
saying you can't make everybody happy is
not true.
Uh
you can't please everybody. That's a
That's not correct. It's not true in in
our
If you understand
how your mind is creating people,
then it then that that means it is
possible to make everybody happy at the
same time.
And that's our goal. That's a
bodhisattva's goal. And you do it by
messing with reality.
And you mess with reality by
understanding
how you are working with archetypes when
you perceive anything, okay? People or
things, okay?
And it's a deep question, and that's
that's DCI advanced level
two. By the way, we're writing advanced
level three right now.
It's based on a really
uh
uh we we're coming out with new books
now the mixed nuts have been going for 6
years Diamond Cutter Classics.
We have we are doing one major book from
every major tradition in 2500 years.
So 100 generations of great books.
We chose the greatest of the greatest.
It's been 6 years.
And we're finishing books books are
starting to come out of the pipeline.
And so we're going to be working DCI
advanced level 3.
We'll be using Ben Cramer's book which
is a study
of
How do I say it?
belief systems systems of belief, okay.
And it's actually
his book Ben's book which is I think
almost 600 pages
is an examination
of 101
ancient belief systems.
All of which are candidates for us.
So it's it's like a candy store
of 101 different belief systems. You
grew up with a belief system
that your parents dumped on you.
And by the way you're you have the right
once you're
16 or so
you have the right to choose your own
belief system. You don't have to follow
necessarily
the one that your parents did my in my
father's generation.
And in my high school
we got 10 days off every autumn
to go out and kill kill deer.
And I was trained to shoot a
high-powered rifle.
And and I was expected to go
kill a deer. Uh I was
expected to leave school for over a week
and go shoot a deer and and and tie it
on top of the car and bring it home.
You know, and I did.
And uh now I reject this belief system.
You see, so anyway, Ben Cramer's book
is an examination of 101
options that you have for
new belief systems.
And it's extremely deep and extremely
beautiful and it includes uh
sections on
uh
enlightened physical activity,
enlightened verbal activity, and
enlightened mental activity. And it's
the first time that I've translated uh
mental
qualities that uh you can develop. It's
a There's a viewpoint
uh the highest one, number one number
one.
Uh which has 110 different mental
trainings you can do.
And we put them all in the book. And uh
so
that's advanced level three.
Which will be coming out
December's again?
I think.
November.
November. Okay. Uh
and then advanced level four is already
being written
for 2024.
And uh that's the gang's book. And I'll
tell you about that when we have more
time.
Uh we're going to take a break, right
Timothy?
Right.
How How long?
25 minutes.
25 minutes? We'll come back at a quarter
to the hour
in most time zones.
Right? And uh we have arranged for the
people here at Diamond Mountain
uh Grandpa has uh
sponsored uh uh
sponsored green drink
or fresh orange juice. So, try to find
it and bring me one, too.
Okay. Thank you. Okay.